Chapter 19 the prophet shipmates have you shipped in that ship?
Quiquang and I had just left the Peekquad, and were sauntering away from
the water, for the moment, each occupied with his own thoughts, when the above
words were put to us by a stranger, who, pausing before us, leveled his massive
forefinger at the vessel in question. He was but shabily apparelled in faded
jacket and patched trousers, a rag of a black handkerchief investing his neck. A
confluent smallpox had in all directions flowed over his face and left it like
the complicated ribbed bed of a torrent when the rushing waters have been dried
up. Have you shipped in her? He repeated. You mean the ship Peekquad? I
suppose, said I, trying to gain a little more time for an uninterrupted look at
him. I the Peekquad. that ship there," he said, drawing back his whole arm, and
then rapidly shoving it straight out from him, with the fixed bayonet of his
pointed finger darted full at the object. "Yes," said I, "we have just
signed the articles." "Anything down there about your souls?" "About what?"
"Oh, perhaps you haven't got any," he said quickly. "No matter, though. I know
many chaps that haven't got any. Good luck to him, and they are all the better
off for it. A soul's a sort of a fifth wheel to a wagon. What are you jabbering
about, shipmate, said I? He's got enough, though, to make up for all
deficiencies of that sort and other chaps. Abruptly, said the stranger,
placing a nervous emphasis upon the word he.
Quiquake, said I, let's go. This fellow is broken loose from somewhere. He's
talking about something and somebody we don't know. Stop!" cried the stranger.
"You said true." "You haven't seen Old Thunder yet, have you?" "Who's Old
Thunder?" said I, again, riveted with the insane earnestness of his manner.
"Captain Ahab?" "What? The captain of our ship, the Peekquad?" "I am Among
some of us old sailor chaps, he goes by that name." "You haven't seen him yet,
have you?" "No, we haven't. He's sick, they say, but is getting better, and
will be all right again before long. All right again before long,
laughed the stranger, with a solemnly derissive sort of laugh. Look ye, when
Captain Ahab is all right, then this left arm of mine will be all right. Not before.
What do you know about him? What did they tell you about him? Say that they
didn't tell much of anything about him.
only. I've heard he's a good whale hunter and a good captain to his crew.
That's true. That's true. Yes, both true enough. But you must jump when he gives
an order. Step and growl. Growl and go.
That's the word with Captain Ahab. But nothing about the thing that happened to
him off Cape Horn long ago when he lay like dead for three days and nights.
Nothing about that deadly scrimmage with the Spaniard before the altar in Santa.
Heard nothing about that, eh? Nothing about the silver calibash he spat into.
And nothing about losing his leg last voyage according to the prophecy. Didn't
you hear a word about them matters and something more, eh? No, I don't think
you did. How could you? Who knows it?
Not all Nantucket, I guess. But how's ever mayap you've heard tell about the
leg and how he lost it. I You have heard of that, I dare say. Oh yes, that
everyone knows most. I mean, they know he's only one leg and that a Parma said
he took the other off. My friend, said I, what all this gibberish of yours is
about, I don't know, and I don't much care, for it seems to me that you must
be a little damaged in the head. But if you are speaking of Captain Ahab of that
ship there, the Peekqua, then let me tell you that I know all about the loss
of his leg. All about it, eh? Sure you do. all pretty sure.
With fingerpointed and eye leveled at the peekquad, the beggar-like stranger
stood a moment, as if in troubled revery, and then, starting a little,
turned and said, "You've shipped. Have you names down on the papers? Well,
well, what's signed is signed, and what's to be will be, and then again,
perhaps it won't be after all. Anyhow, it's all fixed and arranged already, and
some sailors or other must go with him, I suppose. As well these as any other
men, God pity him. A morning to your shipmates. Morning. The ineffable
heavens bless ye. I'm sorry I stopped ye.
Look here, friend, said I. If you have anything important to tell us, out with
it. But if you're only trying to bamboozle us, you're mistaken in your
game. That's all I have to say. And it said very well. And I like to hear a
chap talk up that way. You are just the man for him. The likes of you. Morning
to your shipmates. Morning. Oh, when you get there, tell them I've concluded not
to make one of them. Ah, my dear fellow, you can't fool us that way. You can't
fool us. It is the easiest thing in the
world for a man to look as if he had a great secret in him. Morning to your
shipmates. Morning.
Morning it is, said I. Come along, Quiqu. Let's leave this crazy man. But
stop. Tell me your name, will you?
Elijah.
Elijah, thought I, and we walked away, both commenting after each other's
fashion upon this ragged old sailor, and agreed that he was nothing but a humbug
trying to be a bug bear. But we had not gone perhaps above a h 100red yards when
chancing to turn a corner and looking back as I did so who should be seen but
Elijah following us though at a distance. Somehow the sight of him
struck me so that I said nothing to Quiquake of his being behind but passed
on with my comrade anxious to see whether the stranger would turn the same
corner that we did. He did and then it seemed to me that he was dogging us but
with what intent I could not for the life of me imagine. This circumstance,
coupled with his ambiguous, half-hinting, half-revealing, shrouded
sort of talk, now begat in me all kinds of vague wonderments and half
apprehensions, and all connected with the Peekquad and Captain Ahab, and the
leg he had lost, and the Capehorn fit, and the silver calabash, and what
Captain Pelleg had said of him when I left the ship on the day previous, and
the prediction of the squat tissig, and the voyage we had bound ourselves to
sail, and a hundred other shadowy things. I was resolved to satisfy myself
whether this ragged Elijah was really dogging us or not, and with that intent
crossed the way with Quiqu, and on that side of it retraced our steps. But
Elijah passed on without seeming to notice us. This relieved me, and once
more, and finally, as it seemed to me, I pronounced him in my heart a humbug.